So, we have been discussing why women die which leads to at
the time of childbirth for various sins which leads to a larger
discussion
about how you attribute certain deaths to which type of sins which
obviously raises very serious questions about theodicy and let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara actually will question some of that. But let's
take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says like this, four, three lines from the bottom,
let's pick up from there on ל"ג עמוד ב'. Lamed Gimmel amud
bet. בעוון גזל, Bavon gezel, for the sin of theft, הגובאי עולה,
hagovai oleh, the locust rises up, והרעב הוה, veharav hoveh, and there
is a famine in the land because there is the locust, ובני
אדם אוכלין בשר בניהם ובנותיהם, uvenei adam ochlin besar beneihem uvnoteihem, and
people will eat the flesh of their children, שנאמר, shenemar, the פסוק
pasuk says, שמעו הדבר הזה פרות הבשן אשר בהר שמרון העשקות דלים
הרצצות אביונים, Shim'u hadavar hazeh parot habashan asher behar shomron ha'oshkot dalim
harotzot evyonim, hear this thing, cows of the Bashan which are in
the mountains of
Shomron who oppress the poor and crush the destitute. So and then
the פסוק pasuk ends with,
doesn't quote here the end, no it does, let's take a look,
no yeah, it's about to quote the end in a minute. So
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, כגון הני נשי דמחוזא, kegon hanei neshei deMechuza,
this is like who are these people that are the cows of
the Bashan? So these are the women of מחוזא Mechuza דאכלן ולא
עבדן, de'achlan velo avdan, they eat and they don't do anything like
cows. So even that phrase at the time of the גמרא Gemara
about cows was around.
Dr. Elman from
Revel points out he has a whole like 200 page article, thesis,
or whatever on רבא Rava of מחוזא Mechuza and about how מחוזא
Mechuza was like a cosmopolitan town and רבא Rava was constantly sort
of frustrated with them and they wouldn't listen to him and they
constantly gave him a terrible hard time. So you understand some of
the statements he makes here, particularly about the women of מחוזא Mechuza
and other types of people in his community that he's not happy
with that he's constantly critiquing.
So anyway,
okay, move to the Gemara. How does this still relate?
Well, I don't think the stealing is the women. I think the
women are just אוכלות ולא עובדות ochlot velo ovdot is like the
פרות, parot, like a
cow, it just eats and eats and gets fatter and doesn't do
anything.
Rashi says they eat too much so the men have to go
out to steal.
Oh, that could be. Okay, right, that's what רש"י Rashi says. Okay.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, הכיתי אתכם בשדפון, hikeiti etchem bashidafon,
and now here's how it leads to the locust, I have smitten
you with שדפון, shidafon, which is a wind, ובירקון, uvayerakon, like a
rot, הרבות גנותיכם וכרמיכם ותאניכם וזיתיכם יאכל הגזם. harbot ganoteichem vecharmeichem ute'eneichem
vezeiteichem yochal hagazam. So
that's the end of it. Okay, so in addition to the blasting
wind
and the rot, but all of your vineyards and your figs and
your olives will be eaten by the גזם, gazam, by the locust.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, יתר הגזם אכל הארבה ויתר הארבה אכל הילק ויתר הילק
אכל החסיל, yeter hagazam achal ha'arbeh veyeter ha'arbeh achal hayelek veyeter hayelek
achal hachasil, whatever sort of swarm of locust left over the next
swarm ate. דכתיב, Dechtiv, ויגזר על ימין ורעב ויאכל על שמאל
ולא שבעו, vayigzor al yamin vera'ev vayochal al smolo velo save'u, and
God commanded on the right hand and there was famine
and they ate, and on the left hand and they could not
be satisfied.
איש בשר זרועו יאכלו, ish besar zero'o yocheilu, each man would eat
the flesh of his literally of his arm. אל תקרי בשר זרועו
אלא בשר זרעו, Al tikrei besar zero'o ela besar zar'o, the flesh
of his children obviously in part by פסוקים psukim in the קללה
klala which speak about that explicitly. All right, so now again what's
interesting seems to be actually as we will continue today is that
it doesn't just, it seems more like this is a straight commentary
on פסוקים psukim rather than like speculating oh I wonder why this
happens let's look for a source. It seems that what they're doing
is taking certain explicit biblical פסוקים psukim and just extracting what it's
really saying. And we'll see as it goes actually work through a
lot of the קללה klala today, again without too much speculation, just
really saying look here's the connection being made in the פסוקים. psukim.
So let's take a look. בעוון עינוי הדין ועיוות הדין וקלקול הדין
וביטול תורה, Bavon inuy hadin ve'ivut hadin vekilkul hadin uvitul Torah,
for the sin of oppressing justice and perverting justice and corrupting justice
and neglecting Torah, so how these are exactly different. רש"י Rashi says
that עינוי הדין inuy hadin is שמעכבין את הדין, sheme'akvin et hadin,
that they just postpone it, that they don't actually, they know what
the דין din is and they don't actually get around to making
the decision and it's not
speedy justice. ועיוות הדין Ve'ivut hadin is that they willfully pervert it,
וקלקול הדין vekilkul hadin רש"י Rashi says is that they're just lazy
and it leads to corruption and it leads to perversion even though
it's not willful. Okay, וביטול תורה uvitul Torah and not spending time
in Torah. חרב וביזה רבה, cherev uviza raba, so a sword and
marauding troops and plunder, ודבר ובצורת באה, vedever uvatzoret ba'a, and plague
and famine come. ובני אדם אוכלין ואינם שביעין, uvenei adam ochlin ve'einam
svei'in, and people eat and they're not satisfied, ואוכלין לחמם במשקל, ve'ochlin
lachman bemishkal, and they have to measure out their bread. דכתיב, Dechtiv,
והבאתי עליכם חרב. veheiveiti aleichem cherev. nokemet nekam berit נוקמת נקם ברית,
nokemet nekam berit, I'll bring upon you a sword that avenges the
covenant, right? From the קללות klalot at the end of
ויקרא. Vayikra. ואין ברית אלא תורה, V'ein berit ella torah, ברית berit
means
תורה, Torah, שנאמר אם לא בריתי יומם ולילה חוקות שמים וארץ לא
שמתי. shene'emar im lo beriti yomam valailah chukkot shamayim va'aretz lo shamti.
And how do we know that's talking about the תורה? Torah? So
you could just say what else is it talking about, but I
think Rashi also says it explicitly because it says, you know, והגית
בו יומם ולילה, vehagita bo yomam valailah, so יום ולילה yom v'lailah
refers to the תורה. Torah. וכתיב, Uchtiv, and then the next it
says בשברי לכם מטה לחם, b'shivri lachem mateh lechem, ואפו עשר נשים
לחמכם בתנור אחד, v'afu esser nashim lachmechem b'tanur echad, יען וביען במשפטי
מאסו, yanu biyan b'mishpatai ma'asu, because you have because you have degraded
or disgusted my my laws. Now presumably the יען וביען. yanu biyan.
So anyway, so you get the חרב, cherev, some of this is
like speculating. If there's going to be חרב, cherev, then it leads
to all these other things. It leads to plunder, it leads to
whatever, so it's just drawing out the natural conclusion, although it's not
explicit in the verse. But the question is how do you get
the idea of all this aspect of דין, din, right? Because it's
about תורה. Torah. So now sometimes it's interesting the way the גמרא
Gemara identifies תורה Torah with דין din and the application of תורה
Torah not just as a theoretical pursuit but the actual lived תורה
Torah and practicing it. But again it is interesting because for us
much more that translates more to like personal and private הלכה halakha
rather than in like, you know, sort of דין din which is
sort of like the communal institutions of justice which reflects the different
reality of the society. But it also seems to be that it's
emphasizing במשפטי. b'mishpatai. So it's משפט. mishpat. So there's being מואסין mo'esin
in משפט, mishpat, which also has to do with the עיוות הדין
ivut hadin seems to be the point.
בעוון שבועת שוא ושבועת שקר Ba'avon shvuat shav u'shvuat sheker for the
sin of of an oath for naught and a false oath, so
we all know what a false oath is, an oath for naught
is there's no purpose to it. You take an oath for something
that's obviously true or obviously false, as opposed to שבועת שקר shvuat
sheker where you're actually misleading by the oath. וחילול השם וחילול שבת
חיה רעה רבה ובהמה כלה ובני אדם מתמעטין. V'chilul Hashem v'chilul Shabbat
chaya ra'ah rabbah u'vhemah kalah u'vnei adam mitma'atin. So the evil beasts
increase and the domesticated animals are destroyed and the human and people
are are are the numbers shrink. והדרכים משתוממין V'hadrachim mishtomemin and the
pathways are left are left vacant, desolate. שנאמר ואם באלה לא תוסרו
לי, Shene'emar v'im b'eleh lo tivasru li, and if with these you
do not become sort of remonstrated to me, אל תקרי באלה אלא
באלה. al tikri b'eleh ella b'alah. Don't read with באלה, b'eleh, but
באלה b'alah with the oath. וכתיב, Uchtiv, so that gets you the
שבועת שוא ושבועת שקר. shvuat shav u'shvuat sheker. How about the חילול
השם וחילול שבת? chilul Hashem v'chilul Shabbat? וכתיב, Uchtiv, anyway, but like
here's the consequence, ושלחתי בכם את חית השדה ושכלה
אתכם ונשמו דרכיכם. v'shillachti bachem et chayat hasadeh v'shikkla etchem v'nashamu darcheichem.
So you notice all of this is just straight, you know, the
פסוקים, pesukim, with the consequence, right? It's exactly the straight פסוקים. pesukim.
All it's doing is it's just pointing out what is the exact
correspondence. So it makes a דרשה drasha באלה באלה b'alah b'eleh the
same way before the ברית brit was ברית תורה. brit Torah. So
it's taking what's explicit in the פסוקים pesukim of the various קללות
klalot and trying to just pinpoint and identify the exact the exact
sin which is not explicit in the פסוקים, pesukim, which is made
by a דרשה. drasha. וכתיב Uchtiv by שבועת שקר, shvuat sheker, לא
תשבעו בשמי לשקר וחיללת את שם אלוהיך. lo tishavu bishmi lashaker v'chillalta
et shem elokecha. So שבועת שקר shvuat sheker is חילול השם. chilul
Hashem. ובחילול השם כתיב U'vchilul Hashem ktiv ולא תחללו שם קדשי. v'lo
techalelu shem kodshi. ובחילול שבת כתיב U'vchilul Shabbat ktiv מחלליה מות יומת.
mechaleleha mot yumat. So by שבת Shabbat it doesn't say, it says
those that desecrate, so it's the same word of חילול. chilul. ויליפי
חילול חילול משבועת שקר. V'yalifi chilul chilul mi'shvuat sheker. Make a גזירה
שוה gezera shava of חילול חילול chilul chilul from the false oath.
Okay, so from אלה alah we get שבועה, shvua, from שבועה shvua
we get חילול, chilul, we get שבת Shabbat and we get חילול
השם. chilul Hashem.
Again I don't think, I mean I'm sure you could if you
would want to try to get try to understand more than making
that assignment what's the sort of, you know, symbolic significance of these
punishments for these. I'm not even sure that that, I mean you
could say something, I'm not even sure like I said that that's
exactly the גמרא's Gemara agenda. I think the גמרא's Gemara agenda is
just to try to, you know, although the גמרא Gemara did ask
that by the case of the what do you call it by
the women who die בשעת לידתן, b'sha'at leidatan, what's the connection? But
there it didn't have a פסוק, pasuk, and I think it the
more the agenda like I said is just to try to explain
why bad things happen in the world, not even necessarily like a
מוסר musar and a symbolic explanation, but some way of connecting these
or the opposite, explaining that if you sin, you're going to get
seriously punished, so, you know, it's either to explain why bad things
happen or as general מוסר musar of don't sin here are the
punishments that are waiting for you. Okay, so בעוון שפיכות דמים בית
המקדש חרב ba'avon shfichut damim Beit HaMikdash charev for the sin of
murder the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is destroyed ושכינה מסתלקת מישראל v'shchina
mistalleket mi'Yisrael and the Divine Presence departs from ישראל. Yisrael. שנאמר ולא
תחניפו את הארץ כי הדם הוא יחניף את הארץ ולא תטמא את
הארץ אשר אתם יושבים בה אשר אני שוכן בתוכה. Shene'emar v'lo tachanifu
et ha'aretz ki hadam hu yachanif et ha'aretz v'lo tetamme et ha'aretz
asher atem yoshvim bah asher ani shochen b'tochah. So do not defile
the land which you're dwelling in which I dwell. אתם מטמאים אותה
Atem metammim otah if you do dwell it אינכם יושבים בה einchem
yoshvim bah then you will no longer dwell in it ואיני שוכן
בתוכה. v'eini shochen b'tochah. Okay, so very straightforward there. בעוון גילוי עריות
ועבודה כוכבים ושמיטת Ba'avon gilluy arayot v'avodah kochavim u'shmitat
We had
רציחה, retzicha, so now we have גילוי עריות gilluy arayas and עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, and also שמיטין ויובלות. shmitin v'yovlos. גלות בא לעולם,
Galus ba lo-olam, your exile, which is actually quite clear from the
פסוקים, pesukim, ומגלים אותם ובאים אחרים ויושבים במקומן. u-megalim osam u-vaim acherim
v'yoshvim bimkoman.
That's in the מדרש? Midrash? Right, exactly.
Exactly. Certainly by the שמיטה shmita it's explicit. We'll see how the
גילוי עריות gilluy arayas and עבודה זרה. avoda zara. ומגלים אותם ובאים
אחרים ויושבים במקומן. U-megalim osam u-vaim acherim v'yoshvim bimkoman. So specifically I
mean I don't know how גלות בא לעולם galus ba lo-olam ומגלים
אותן, u-megalin otan, but anyway somehow God is involved in sending you
into exile and others come and take your place. שנאמר כי את
כל התועבות האל עשו אנשי הארץ, Shene'emar ki es kol ha-to'evos ha-eil
asu anshei ha-aretz, וכתיב ותטמא הארץ ואפקוד עוונה עליה. v'chsiv vatitma ha-aretz
va-efkod avonah aleha.
Maybe part of the difference also is that notice here it's, you
know, it's, yeah, you know, here it's like בא לעולם. ba lo-olam.
I'm looking before if they had the phrase בא לעולם. ba lo-olam.
I mean they spoke in generic terms, but here it could also
be that the non-Jews as well, those that lived in the land
were exiled because of this. So it's not just the way the
Jews are punished, right? And then so the Jews took their place
and they don't have the same thing happen to you. ואפקוד עוונה
עליה, va-efkod avonah aleha, וכתיב ולא תקיא הארץ אתכם בטמאכם אותה כאשר
קאה את הגוי אשר לפניכם, v'chsiv v'lo sakia ha-aretz es-chem b'tamacha-chem osah
ka'asher ka'ah es ha-goy asher lifneichem, right?
So it's exactly that.
And how do we know what the תועבות to'evos are? ובעבודת כוכבים
כתיב ונתתי את פגריכם על פגרי גילוליכם. U-v'avodas kochavim ksiv v'nasati es
pigreichem al pigrei gilluleichem. So פגריכם pigreichem your corpses,
פגרי גילוליכם pigrei gilluleichem are the corpses of your idols or the
you know. And the תועבות האל ha-to'evos ha-eil is right after the
whole פרשה parsha of עריות, arayas, so by juxtaposition obviously that's עריות.
arayas. וכתיב והשמותי את מקדשיכם, V'chsiv v'hashimoti es mikdesheichem, I will lay
waste your sanctuaries. ואתכם אזרה בגויים, V'eschem ezareh va-goyim, I will scatter
you amongst the nations.
So there it's pretty, there very much fits in the context in
these two separate cases. ובשמיטין וביובלות כתיב אז תרצה הארץ את שבתותיה
כל ימי השמה ואתם בארץ אויביכם. U-v'shmitin u-v'yovlos ksiv az tirtzeh ha-aretz
es shabbososeha kol yemei hashamah v'atem b'eretz oyveichem. Yeah,
that's quite explicit in בהר, Behar, that it's all about not keeping
שמיטה. shmita. וכתיב כל ימי השמה תשבות, V'chsiv kol yemei hashamah tishbos,
and
when it is lay desolate then it will rest and recover from
the fact that you did not keep שמיטות shmitos when you were
in it. בעוון נבלות פה. Ba-avon nivlus peh. Now this is interesting,
because until now it's all been very explicit עבירות. aveiros. And here
actually the גמרא, Gemara, you know, the idea of נבלות פה, nivlus
peh, like I don't know about you, but growing up certainly as
a high school kid you heard a lot about נבלות פה. nivlus
peh.
And where exactly is that in the not in your public high
school? Anyway, where exactly is that in the פסוקים? pesukim? נה Nah
I mean, you know, the רמב"ן Ramban says and the
פסוק pasuk קדושים תהיו, Kedoshim Tihyu, he says why does it say
קדושים תהיו? Kedoshim Tihyu? Because you have to live up to the
values even when it's not a מצווה. mitzvah. And one of the
examples he gives is נבלות פה, nivlus peh, right? It's not a
מצווה mitzvah anywhere, but that's part of קדושים תהיו. Kedoshim Tihyu. So
anyway this גמרא Gemara in the middle of all of this explanation
of why bad things happen or what certain thing, what punishments are
waiting for certain things introduces a new problem of נבלות פה. nivlus
peh. So let's take a look. בעוון נבלות פה, Ba-avon nivlus peh,
for the sake of sort of, you know,
what's a good translation for
what נבלות? nivlus? Foul mouth, degenerate mouth? Anyway. צרות רבות וגזירות קשות
מתחדשות, Tzaros rabbos u-gezeiros kashos mis-chadshos, so new great afflictions and new
edicts, difficult edicts are coming to the world. ובחורי שונאי ישראל מתים
יתומים ואלמנות צועקים ואינם נענים. U-vachurei sonei Yisrael mesim yesomim v'almanos tzo'akim
v'einam ne'anim. And now it specifically mentions ישראל, Yisrael, so it becomes
שונאי ישראל. sonei Yisrael. The young ones of Israel die, orphans excuse
me,
מתים mesim die, orphans and widows cry out and they're not answered.
שנאמר על כן על בחוריו לא ישמח השם, Shene'emar al kein al
bachurav lo yismach Hashem, therefore God will not rejoice over His youth.
ואת יתומיו ואת אלמנותיו לא ירחם, V'es yesomav v'es almanosav lo yerachem,
and He will not have compassion on the orphans and on the
widows. So we assume the first one means that they will die
and the second one means He will not respond to them. כי
כולו חנף ומרע, Ki kulo chanef u-meira, because all of them are
sort of
flattering and speaking evil. וכל פה דובר נבלה,
V'chol peh dover
nevalah,
and all so that's נבלות פה nivlus peh all mouth speaks foul
matter, about filth.
But he probably means Isaiah probably means the idolatry, right?
Oh that's interesting.
I mean in the context, right?
It's interesting. I wonder what the מפרשים mefarshim say there.
חנף ומרע Chanef u-meira is not necessarily idolatry, right? That's true. I
wonder what, I want
to see, you have
all your תנ"ך Tanakh at my house now. Really? That's funny.
Oh because you brought it for last night? Right. Okay. I will
have to look that out.
Okay, where were we? ובכל זאת לא שב אפו ועוד ידו נטויה.
U-v'chol zos lo shav apo v'od yado netuyah. And His anger is
not, even after punishing, His anger has not gone back and His
arm is still stretched out.
מאי ועוד ידו נטויה? Mai v'od yado netuyah? His arm is still
stretched out. אמר רב חנן בר רבא הכל יודעים כלה למה נכנסה
לחופה. Amar Rav Chanan bar Rava ha-kol yod'im kallah lamah nichnesah l'chuppah.
Everybody knows why the bride is entering into the חופה. chuppah. It's
also interesting already the focus on the bride, not on the groom,
right? אלא כל המנבל פיו אפילו חותמים עליו גזר דין של שבעים
שנה לטובה הופכים עליו לרעה. Ella kol ha-menavel piv afilu chosmim alav
gezar din shel shiv'im shanah l'tovah hofchim alav l'ra'ah. But anybody that
actually makes his mouth foul, even if they seal for him a
decree of seventy years for good, they turn it over for evil.
his mouth foul by talking about such matters, even if they have
a 70 years for having done good and you have a גזר
דין, gzar din, it’ll all turn over against you for evil. So
it’s pretty heavy, right? But it is interesting again, you know, because
normally you assume and even the גמרא Gemara assumes, like, the male
sex drive is more than the female tends to be the general
assumption of the גמרא, Gemara, all the laws of ייחוד yichud and
all of that.
So it’s interesting, it might reflect just that sort of male perspective
that, you know, so the objectifying of women and so you’re talking
about them, you’re talking about the women, but it’s but it’s still
funny because at least you’re talking about them not so much as
objects, you’re talking about why is she doing it, you know, you’re
sort of talking about her more as the sort of the subject
of the matter.
Do you think הפכיה לשולחנא hafichah lashulchana has a sexual connotation there?
Oh, like הפיכת השולחן? hafichat hashulchan?
I don’t know. I also want to know what this gets from
עוד ידו נטויה, od yado netuyah, like what’s the connection? You know,
it just means that this is such a terrible thing? I mean,
is there you would be looking for, like, some connection of words
or something about how they translated it into שבעים שנה, shivim shana,
how they translated into, you know, I don’t even know, you know,
I really don’t get the exact connection. Yeah, I don’t think רש''י
Rashi helps.
Okay, so let’s see as the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, אמר רבה בר שילא אמר רב חסדא כל המנבל פיו. Amar
Rabbah bar Shila amar Rav Chisda kol hamenavel piv. So now that
we’re talking about ניבול פה, nibul peh, notice we sort of digress
a bit because this is something we don’t normally explore. So
כל המנבל פיו מעמיקים לו גיהנם. kol hamenabel piv maamikin lo Gehennom.
So they make גיהנם Gehennom even deeper for you. שנאמר שוחה עמוקה
פי זרות.
shene'emar shucha amuka pi
zarot.
So a deep, like, pit for the mouth of, you know, perversity
is how it’s being read here. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר אף
שומע ושותק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar af shome'a v'shoteik. Not only
the one who speaks it, but even the one who hears and
doesn’t really react. שנאמר זעום ה' יפול שם. shene'emar ze'um Hashem yipol
sham.
The, I don’t know, normally it probably means, like, the one who,
like, angers God will fall there.
רש''י Rashi says זעמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא שורה שם אצל פי
זרות והיושב אצלו ושומע קרוי זעומו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. za'amo shel
Hakadosh Baruch Hu shora sham etzel pi zarot vehayoshev etzlo v'shome'a karui
ze'umo shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. So I’ve no idea what the connection
is about here about זעום, ze'um, the one who angers God is
the one who listens and does not respond. But I will tell
you, maybe, you know, I don’t know if you want to call
it in the context of ניבול פה, nibul peh, but this is
something I certainly get challenged with when, you know, when somebody says
sort of, like, racist remarks or other types of things, you know,
it’s always the question about do you let it go or do
you start a whole fight and how much do you say something
or not say something, you know, especially in our role as rabbis.
So nibul person saying, oh, I can’t curse in front of the
rabbi.
Right. Do you like brush it away or what do you do?
Right. But yeah, to me, to me the much more challenging one
is, like, like I said, when people really say, like,
very inappropriate things and how much do you say, like, you know,
that’s really not acceptable here or whatever, how would you want to
start a fight or not? But it’s anyway, some real some real
מוסר. mussar. Okay, אמר רב אושעיא כל הממרק עצמו לעבירה חבורות ופצעים
יוצאין בו. Amar Rav Oshaya kol hamamreik atzmo l'aveira chaburot u'ptzaim yotzin
bo. Anybody who empties himself out for sin, meaning like sort of
completely devotes himself, focuses on sinning, pursues it, then, you know, a
wounds and a and wounds, I don’t know,
will come out from him. שנאמר חבורות פצע תמרוק ברעה. shene'emar chaburot
petza tamruk b'ra'ah. So the wounds of smiting will one who, it's
being read here, empties himself, pours himself out in evil. ולא עוד
אלא שנידון בהידרוקן. v'lo od ela shenidon behidrokan. And you’re
judged with הידרוקן, hidrokan, which is some type of a disease. שנאמר
ומכות חדרי בטן. shene'emar u'makot chadrei vaten. And some type of intestinal
disease. ומכות חדרי בטן, u'makot chadrei vaten, and, you know, plagues of
the innermost intestines. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק סימן לעבירה הידרוקן. Amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak siman l'aveira hidrokan. Now it’s, you
know, we’re going to actually reverse it. If you’ve taken, like, a
class of logic, if P then Q does not mean if Q
then P, right? So if it rains we won’t go to the
game doesn’t mean if we didn’t go to the game it was
because it rained. But until now, the גמרא Gemara has been saying
if you do this, this is how you’re going to get punished.
Now the גמרא Gemara is actually going to say if this is
what you’re suffering, it tells us what you, how you sinned, which
is a much more sort of dangerous, you know, type of a
theology. So let’s take a look at what it says. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to deal with the consequences of that in
a minute. סימן לעבירה הידרוקן. siman l'aveira hidrokan. If you have this
הידרוקן, hidrokan, this intestinal sort of illness, disease, then it’s a סימן
siman that you sinned. תנו רבנן ג' מיני הידרוקן הן. Tanu Rabbanan
gimel minei hidrokan hen. There are three types. של עבירה עבה, shel
aveira avei, the one that comes as a result of sin is
thick. רש''י Rashi says I think it means that your skin is
very thick, like your skin gets hard and it sort of, like,
bloats. ושל רעב תפוח, v'shel ra'av tapuach, the one that comes as
a result of famine, תפוח, tapuach, so that leads to a type
of also like a blowing up of the skin. ושל כשפים דק,
v'shel kshafim dak, the one that comes as a result of witchcraft,
I assume it means witchcraft done on you or maybe you’ve done
witchcraft, דק, dak, makes your skin very brittle and thin. שמואל הקטן
חש ביה. Shmuel hakatan chash bei. So שמואל הקטן Shmuel hakatan had
this הידרוקן. hidrokan. אמר Amar he said... Shmuel Hakatan had this הדרוקין.
hadropikin. אמר, amar, he said, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, Master
of the World, מי מפיס? mi mafis? Who's going to throw lot,
meaning who's going to be able to discern
that this is not as a result of sin? People will think
I'm a sinner. איתפסי, itpasi, so he got better. אביי חש ביה.
Abaye chash beh. Abaye had this.
That sounds sorcery to me. What? That sounds sorcery to me.
I
was talking to God. אביי חש ביה. Abaye chash beh. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so Rava said, ידנא ביה בנחמני, Yadana beih b'Nachmani, I
know Nachmani, which was some say
it was like a what do you call it, the original name
of Abaye and some say it was a nickname of Abaye, but
anyway, I know
Nachmani, דמכפי נפשיה, de'machpi nafshei, that he fasts himself, he starves himself,
he goes on a lot of תעניות, ta'aniyot, and that's why he
had this, because one of the things had to do with famine.
רבא חש ביה, Rava chash beh, Rava had this. והא רבא הוא
דאמר, V'ha Rava hu d'amar, נפישי דקטילי קדר מנפישי דכפן. nepishi d'ketili
k'dar minepishi de'chafan. Doesn't Rava say that greater are those that die
from קדר, k'dar, which is Rashi says like holding back your like
a pot you pour out your
pot means holding back when you need to go to the bathroom,
and that that causes this illness more than those that actually fast?
So it's another sort of very medical physical cause for the illness
is that you understand that you didn't actually go to the bathroom
when you needed to. So what does that prove? So we knew
Rava didn't fast himself, didn't do תענית. ta'anit. We knew he was
so sensitive to this other issue about going to the bathroom when
he needed to. So there's no good physical cause for this, so
what's the explanation? Is it sin? How can you say that? Gemara
says no, שאני רבא דאניסו ליה רבנן בעידני בעל כרחיה. shani Rava
d'aniseh lei rabanan be'idnei b'al korchei. No, the rabbis are always nudging
him and asking him more questions when he's got to go to
the bathroom. So sometimes he's not able to go to the bathroom
when he needs to and that's what brought it about. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan.
That's my דרשה drasha for this month.
All right,
please, please no talking during קידוש. Kiddush. שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom.
All
right. תנו רבנן ארבעה סימנין הן. Tanu rabanan arba'ah simanim hen. There
are four signs. סימן לעבירה הדרוקן. Siman la'averah hadrokan. If you want
to know
the sign for sin is that somebody has this intestinal disease. סימן
לשנאת חנם, Siman lesinas chinam, how about somebody has purposeless hatred, ירקון,
yerakon,
some type of jaundice. סימן לגסות הרוח, Siman legasus haruach, somebody is
haughty, usually you don't need סימנים simanim for that. Anyway, עניות. aniyut.
So the person becomes poor. סימן ללשון הרע אסכרה, Siman lilashon hara
askara, for evil tongue, אסכרה, askara, which is a breathing
croup or something, some type of a respiratory illness. תנו רבנן אסכרה
באה לעולם, Tanu rabanan askara ba'ah la'olam, אסכרה askara comes to the
world על המעשר, al hama'aser,
for not giving the tithes. So רש״י Rashi says that since if
you eat טבל tevel the punishment is מיתה בידי שמים mita bidei
shamayim and it has to do with eating, so that's this type
of a, you know, one on the upper body although this is
more respiratory rather than digestive, but anyway. רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אומר
על לשון הרע. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose omer al lashon hara.
For evil tongue, presumably also has to do with your mouth and
so on. אמר רבא ואיתימא רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rava ve'itema
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, מאי קרא? mai kra? Where do you see
it from the פסוק? pasuk? והמלך ישמח באלוהים יתהלל כל הנשבע בו,
Ve'hamelech yismach belohim yithalel kol hanishba bo,
the king will rejoice in God or will be praised all who
swears in His name, כי יסכר פי דוברי שקר, ki yisacher pi
dovrei shaker,
because will be sort of like silenced the mouth of all who
speak falsehood. But here it's explaining יסכר yisacher means from the word
אסכרה, askara, all who speak falsehood. I should say calling it לשון
הרע, lashon hara, we normally assume לשון הרע lashon hara is like
slander, you know, whether it's true or not, or speaking ill of
people, but here you see a different meaning for לשון הרע lashon
hara which is also I think very much in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
which is it just means like all types of bad forms of
speech. So lying is also a type of לשון הרע. lashon hara.
But לשון הרע lashon hara is more generic, any ways in which
you do evil with your speech. Right. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, so
they asked, רבי אלעזר ברבי
יוסי על לשון הרע קאמר או דלמא אף על לשון הרע קאמר.
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose al lashon hara kama o dilma af al
lashon hara kama. When he's saying that you get this for לשון
הרע, lashon hara, which we just said, right, so was he saying
this only for לשון הרע lashon hara or even for לשון הרע?
lashon hara? The only reason we're asking is because we're going to
have another statement that says which will make us say that he's
saying even for לשון הרע. lashon hara. תא שמע, Tashma, come hear.
כשנכנסו רבותינו לכרם ביבנה. Keshenichnesu raboteinu l'Kerem b'Yavne. When our sages went
into the
vineyard of Yavne when they, the assembly, see here's the rabbinic assembly
right after the חורבן בית המקדש, churban Beis Hamikdash, the rabbis all
got together. היה שם רבי יהודה ורבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי ורבי שמעון.
Haya sham Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Shimon. So there
were these three rabbis: Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose, and Rabbi
Shimon. נשאלו לשאלה זו בפניהם. Nish'alu lish'eilah zu bifneihem. So they raised
the following question: מכה זו מפני מה מתחלת בבני מעיים וגומרת בפה?
Maka zu mipnei mah matchala bivne me'ayim v'gomeres bepeh? Why does this
plague, illness, start in the intestines and end in the mouth? Right,
it comes up and it causes respiratory illness and so on. Now
what I think is quite fascinating is you wouldn't have imagined כרם
ביבנה Kerem b'Yavne was all about bringing together, I mean מסכת עדיות
Maseches Eduyos was taught then getting all the testimony, saving תורה שבעל
פה Torah sheba'al peh and so on and you would not imagine
that they would be spending time so like discussing why the illnesses
start in. Maybe that was I don't know that was their breaks
or something or that was their little שמוזינג shmoozing before they got
down to the brass tacks. But no, it does make you wonder
how much you know was sort of like theological speculation part of
what they were doing that we don't really, you know, it's not
really on our radar screen. I mean look, אגדתא aggadata in the
גמרא Gemara is basically theological speculation. And how much do we think
in this whole idea of Yavneh preserving תורה שבעל פה Torah She-be'al
Peh was part that part of it? I don't, you know, so
it's interesting that this is sort of like one of the focuses
of their conversation.
But could you imagine if we were to talk about simply like
what caused...
Right. Exactly. Exactly. So right, and if it's a very common illness
and you want to understand what it's about, right, it's like specifically
מכה זו, maka zu, something that is a really major issue and
trying to get a handle on it theologically.
And also, you know, in post sort of temple destruction, right, it's
in some ways comforting to imagine that God sort of has a
hand in all things, large and small, that that gives the sense
that there's still order in the world.
Aha. Right. Right. Right. There's still השגחה hashgacha and He's
involved in our lives. That's a nice point as well. Very good.
Alright so he says, so תנא tanna רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי, Rabbi
Yehuda berabbi Ilai, so Rabbi Yehuda berabbi Ilai is סתם רבי יהודה
stam Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה, Mishna, תלמיד רבי עקיבא, talmid Rabbi
Akiva, answers: ראש המדברים בכל מקום. Rosh Hamedabrim bechol makom. He
is the one that gets to speak first everywhere. We'll see what
that means in a minute. ואמר, Va'amar, אף על פי שכליות יועצות,
af al pi shekelayot yoatzot, even though the kidneys advise, right, because
in the ancient world the kidneys were seen as the metaphorical like
sort of, you know, in terms of like we like we speak
about the brain or whatever, but the kidneys
advise, ולב
מבין, velev mevin, the heart understands, ולשון מחתך, velashon mechatech, and the
and the tongue cuts like enunciates, פה גומר, peh gomer, the mouth
finishes. So,
so in terms of so רש"י Rashi says, you know, פה גומר
לשון הרע. peh gomer lashon hara. Okay, so it's again tying back
into the לשון הרע, lashon hara, so even though it comes, it
begins in other parts of the body it ends in the mouth.
And therefore this, this is an illness which begins in other parts
of the body but ultimately rises up into the throat and into
the mouth.
In other words, it takes the same course as the sin.
Exactly, exactly.
Okay, so that's what he said.
תנא רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי, Tanna Rabbi Elazar berabbi Yose, so Rabbi
Elazar berabbi Yose who before said לשון הרע lashon hara and he
said,
דאמר מפני שאוכלין בדברים טמאין, de'amar mipnei she'ochlin bidevarim tme'in, because you
eat non-kosher food. So גמרא Gemara says, דברים טמאין סלקא דעתך? devarim
tme'in salka da'atach? Is that possible? So now why is it is
that possible, meaning do we suspect that everybody who's gets this is
being עובר over on it? Maybe, you know, how many people are
eating חזיר? chazir? רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י Rashi
the last of the wide lines,
דברים טמאין סלקא דעתך ועונשא מיתה? devarim tme'in salka da'atach ve'onsha mita?
דאפילו על לשון הרע עונשה מיתה דכתיב מלשני בסתר רעהו אותו אצמית.
de'afilu al lashon hara onsha mita dechtiv malshni baseter re'ehu oto atzmit.
So רש"י Rashi says no because other non-kosher things it's a לאו,
lav, it's not מיתה. mita. So we couldn't understand this, you know,
the proportion, we couldn't understand the degree of punishment being deserved, that's
the way רש"י Rashi reads it. אלא שאוכלין בדברים שאינם מתוקנים, Ela
she'ochlin bidevarim she'einam metukanim, they eat things that are טבל, tevel, and
טבל tevel is חייב מיתה בידי שמים, chayav mita bidei shamayim, and
that's one of the answers we said before. Okay, so before that
was an answer prior to רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי. Rabbi Elazar berabbi
Yose. רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar berabbi Yose said לשון הרע.
lashon hara. Here רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar berabbi Yose is
saying the טבל tevel or non-kosher food.
תנא רבי שמעון ואמר, Tanna Rabbi Shimon va'amar, Rabbi Shimon says got
up and said, בעוון ביטול תורה, ba'avon bitul Torah, for not doing
Torah. Now I said before that here the גמרא Gemara actually after
a whole דף daf and more of saying this for this and
this for this and here's why you get this punishment, here the
גמרא Gemara actually questions it. But we'll see what the answer is.
Anybody who gets אסכרה askara is because of ביטול תורה? bitul Torah?
So גמרא Gemara says, אמרו לו נשים יוכיחו. amru lo nashim yochi'u.
How about women? They're not מצוות תורה metzuvot Torah and they get
אסכרה. askara. So he said, he has an answer, שמבטלות את בעליהן.
shemvatlot et ba'aleihen. They cause their husbands to be מבטל mevatel from
תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah. So they get this punishment.
Okay. נכרים יוכיחו. Nochrim yochi'u. How about non-Jews? Now that's fascinating too,
right? Because this whole idea why do bad things happen, actually look
outside of the Jewish world, right? So why do non-Jews get it?
Now how about why did non-Jews get it if it's לשון הרע
lashon hara maybe? But how about אוכלין דברים טמאין? ochlin devarim tme'in?
I don't know why that question didn't come up there. Maybe because
of אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, which is חייב מיתה chayav
mita for
בני
נח. bnei Noach. Okay, anyway. So נכרים יוכיחו. nochrim yochi'u. So the
answer is, שמבטלין את ישראל. shemvatlin et Yisrael. Oh no, because of
whatever, you know, their גזירות gzeirot and because of other things, just
the, you know, demands that they put up upon us that causes
us not to be able to fully invest in תלמוד תורה. talmud
Torah. תינוקות יוכיחו. Tinokot yochi'u. How about the fact that young children
get it? Right? What have they done of ביטול תורה? bitul Torah?
שמבטלין את אביהן. Shemvatlin et avihen. Yeah, because they cried getting up
in the middle of the night. Now obviously the problem here is
that, you know, why do they deserve it though, they're not בני
עונשין, bnei onshin, right? So somehow there's some more sort of like,
you know, metaphysical karma here, you know, if they do it, it's
a, it's not so much of a punishment for, you know, for
sin. But somehow, anyway, so it certainly raises serious questions.
What? Any parent knows a sick kid is more punishment for the
parents.
Right. No, but I'm saying this is raises serious questions, you know,
because the גמרא Gemara before, I think it was the גמרא Gemara
or I'm losing a little track of naming what, was about, you
know, children dying for the sins of their fathers, right? So... is
actually is grappling with the פסוקים, pesukim, on the one לא יומתו
אבות על בנים lo yumsu avos al banim and the other, you
know, פוקד עון אבות על בניכם, poked avon avos al beneichem, and
so on. But then there was this understanding, you know, that a
person's children and sometimes a man's wife were like his sort of,
you know, look at איוב, Iyov, how's איוב Iyov punished? Right? His
kids die and his cows die and there's a sense that this
is yours and that's a way that you get punished. But the
idea that the children are punished for their own sin and when
they're so young is in a way, you know, more radical or
less, you know, less something that we would see. So
it's quite, it's quite interesting that that's his answer for the
תינוקות. tinokos. So תינוקות, tinokos, now maybe again, תינוקות, tinokos, sometimes you
don't know exactly what the age is. We say תינוקות tinokos means
infants, sometimes תינוקות tinokos could just mean young. So maybe that's the
shift from this answer, which is תינוקות של בית רבן יוכיחו. tinokos
shel beis rabban yochichu.
How about those that are in their, you know, Rebbe's home? Now,
presumably, what is so, either they maybe, maybe they're older, so they're
not crying in the middle of the night, or maybe it's the
opposite, like maybe they're young, they're very small and they're younger and
we can't understand why. So that's what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi
says the first תינוקות tinokos were אינם בני לימוד, einam bnei limud,
okay, and therefore they're just babies crying in the crib. But what
about those that are actually sitting and learning in חדר? cheder? What
are they doing wrong? They're learning all day. So the גמרא Gemara
says התם כרבי גוריון. hasam kerabbi goryon.
That's like רבי גוריון, Rabbi Goryon, דאמר רבי גוריון ואיתימא רבי יוסי
ברבי ישמעאל בזמן שהצדיקים בדור צדיקים נתפסים על הדור. d'amar Rabbi Goryon
v'isayma Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Yishmael bizman she'tzaddikim b'dor tzaddikim nitpasim al hador.
When there are righteous people in the generation, then they will sometimes
be punished for the sake of the generation, they'll suffer the punishment
that's deserving on others. אין צדיקים בדור תינוקות של בית רבן נתפסים
על הדור. ein tzaddikim b'dor tinokos shel beis rabban nitpasim al hador.
If there's no צדיקים, tzaddikim, you take the most innocent. The most
innocent are the תינוקות של בית רבן. tinokos shel beis rabban. Right.
אמר רבי יצחק בר זעירי ואמרי לה אמר רבי שמעון בן נזירה,
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ze'iri v'amrei lah Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Nezira,
מאי קרא? mai kra?
Where do you see in the פסוק? pasuk? אם לא תדעי לך
היפה בנשים, im lo sadi lach hayafa banashim,
if you do not know, oh beautiful among women, צאי לך בעקבי
הצאן, tzei lach b'ikvei hatzon, go out, you know, by the footsteps
of the
sheep, ורעי את גדיותיך על משכנות הרועים, u'rei es gediyosayich al mishkenos
haro'im, and, you know, shepherd your flock by the tents of the
רועים. ro'im. What does this mean? במיני גדיים הממושכנים על הרועים. b'mini
gediyim hameshukanim al haro'im. So על משכנות הרועים al mishkenos haro'im from
the word משכון. mashkon. They are collateral for the רועים. ro'im. The
shepherds are the leaders of the generation. So if there are no
leaders of the generation that are צדיקים, tzaddikim, then these are like
the collateral for the עם, am, and that they, the innocent, suffer
as a result of the sin of others. So on the one
hand, it's something, I mean, I'm wondering why you're saying wow so
many times. On the one hand, it's something we don't like to
admit because of any, you know, after Christianity, the idea of an
innocent suffering for others' sins and vicarious punishment is something we like
to believe is not part of Judaism. But, you know, you read
on, you know, just like, I don't know, in the Birnbaum or
the classic, you know, סידור, siddur, like why do we say the
עשרה הרוגי מלכות asara harugei malchus on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? מיתת
צדיקים מכפרת, misas tzaddikim mechaperes, and they're like a קרבן, korban, and
so on. So it's not like these ideas are foreign to Judaism,
I mean. So and here you have, like, the most innocent suffer
somehow as a result of, as a result of the generation. I
don't know what to do with, how are you going to use
that in a sermon? Theologically troubling. Yeah, deeply. Yeah, right, right. There's
certainly a real question about how you deal with a lot of
this, you know, a, the infants dying for their own sin, and
then dying for the sins of others, right? And the way, like
I said, the idea of vicarious punishment is more, I think, you
know,
present in texts than the idea of somebody who's an infant dying
for the fact that they're crying in the middle of the night
and waking up their parent for their own sin. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. Where
were we? So אמר רבי יצחק בר זעירי ואמרי לה אמר רבי
שמעון... Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ze'iri v'amrei lah Amar Rabbi Shimon... we
just did that. שמע מינה, shema mina, so אף על לשון הרע
קאמר. af al lashon hara kama. שמע מינה. shema mina. So you
forgot why we brought this in, it's to prove that רבי אלעזר
ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose, first he said לשון הרע, lashon
hara, and here we see he says that they eat, you know,
non-kosher things, which meant טבל, tevel, so you see he means even
לשון הרע. lashon hara. Okay, that's a good proof. Okay, now we
get into a nice interesting
digression, this you're going to enjoy. ואמאי קרו ליה ראש המדברים בכל
מקום? v'amai karu lei rosh hamedabrim bechol makom? Why was רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda called the head speaker at all times? דיתבי רבי יהודה
ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון, d'yasvi Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Shimon, you
might be familiar with the story. רבי יהודה, רבי יוסי, ורבי שמעון
Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Yose and Rabbi Shimon were sitting in a meeting,
in a whatever, maybe כרם ביבנה Kerem b'Yavne again, ויתיב יהודה בן
גרים גבייהו, v'yasiv Yehuda ben Gerim gabaihu, and יהודה בן גרים, Yehuda
ben Gerim,
right, who was the son of
converts, was sitting among them. פתח רבי יהודה ואמר. Pasach Rabbi Yehuda
v'amar. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda opened and said, כמה נאים מעשיהם של
אומה זו. kama na'im ma'aseihem shel uma zu. How wonderful are the
actions of this nation of Rome. תיקנו שווקים, tiknu shvakin,
they made marketplaces, תיקנו גשרים, tiknu gisharin, they made bridges, תיקנו מרחצאות,
tiknu merchaza'os, bathhouses. רבי יוסי שתק. Rabbi Yose shasak. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose didn't
say anything. נענה רבי שמעון בר יוחאי ואמר. Na'ana Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai v'amar. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai got up
and
said, כל מה שתיקנו לא תיקנו אלא לצורך
עצמן. kol mah shetiknu lo tiknu ela l'tzorech atzman. What are you
talking about? They're all doing it out just for their own self-interest.
תיקנו שווקים להושיב בהן זונות, tiknu shvakin l'hoshiv bahen zonos, they made
these marketplaces to put in prostitutes, מרחצאות merchaza'os to beautify themselves. גשרים
ליטול מהם מכס, gsharim litol mehem meches, the bridges are for collecting
taxes. So it's all for their own interest.
So of course if anybody knows, this was of course most beautifully
portrayed in Monty Python's Life of Brian.
Right? Classic. You know the scene? It's a brilliant מדרש. Medrash. It's
not even a מדרש, Medrash, it's just, anyway, it's a great, okay,
okay, okay. So now the whole story, this
whole story that רש"י Rashi's brought to show you that פתח רבי
יהודה. patach Rabbi Yehuda.
What, yeah, no, פתח רבי יהודה, patach Rabbi Yehuda, that whole thing,
where it says that רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yossi
said one thing and we had a whole big story about where,
about why אסקרה askara happens, which started with פתח רבי יהודה. patach
Rabbi Yehuda. And now we're focusing on the פתח רבי יהודה patach
Rabbi Yehuda and getting into this whole discussion, right?
But it's a, it's a great story. Anyway, I should say by
the way it's interesting, you know, it does lead to general obviously
a broader question about how do you look at, you know, the
larger, tying in a little bit to our theme today, but you
know, the larger non-Jewish world.
I just taught this text, I did a whole thing about, you
know, American Judaism basically, how Americans view, how Jews should view, and
this
is, exactly, exactly, yeah I mean, you know, you could interpret, you
know, things radically differently, you know. Do you have that sense of
gratitude? Or do you say, eh, why should we be grateful? They're
all doing it for themselves, we're just, you know, incidental beneficiaries, you
know? But it's this issue about cultivating and especially trying to cultivate
a sense of gratitude amongst the Romans who were constantly oppressing the
Jews, it's pretty amazing. It is interesting that in the beginning of
מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avodah Zarah,
this text gets quoted, or a slice of it, but only the
negative part. So the גמרא, Gemara, the very opening סוגיא sugya of
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, the גמרא Gemara sort of says about like
לעתיד לבוא, l'asid lavo, God's going to take all of the nations
to judgment and He's going to say, pick Rome in front and
say, what did you do? You know, oh we, look at what
we did to help ישראל Yisrael learn תורה, Torah, we made מרחצאות,
merchatzaos, we made שווקים, shvakim, we made, He says, no, you only
did it לצורך עצמכם, l'tzorech atzmachem, blah blah blah. So God becomes
now רבי שמעון בר יוחאי's Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai's position is put
in the mouth of God in the first סוגיא sugya in עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. So that's interesting. I mean, you know, every, every,
it's like, it's not like there's one, I mean I don't have
to tell you this, it's not like there's the גמרא Gemara says,
so because עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah says that, that means whatever, but
different גמרות Gemoras take different approaches and it's interesting that that's the
approach it chooses to open מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah with.
So, which is much more about non-Jewish world than it is about
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, let's
take a look. הלך יהודה בן גרים וסיפר דבריהם. Halach Yehuda ben
Gerim v'siper divreihem. יהודה בן גרים Yehuda ben Gerim went and he
was just talking, you know, רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean he
was reporting and informing on them, he was just schmoozing at home.
But you know, his home had also some people that originally were
non-Jews, maybe some people that were still non-Jews, רש"י Rashi says maybe
he meant, you know, so therefore they said it to their friends
and somehow one thing led to another, ונשמעו למלכות, v'nishmu l'malchus, it
got heard by the, by the, by the government. אמרו, Amru, so
the government said, יהודה שעילה, Yehuda she'ila, יהודה Yehuda that praised us,
יתעלה, yisaleh, he will be given, he will be raised up. And
therefore he was given right by the government at any convocation to
be the first speaker. That's why he was ראש המדברים בכל מקום.
rosh hamedabrim b'chol makom. That's why we brought this whole thing in
to that phrase of ראש המדברים. rosh hamedabrim. And now we continue
with the story. יוסי ששתק, Yossi sheshatak, יוסי Yossi who was silent,
יגלה לציפורי, yigaleh l'Tzipori, let him go be exiled to Tzipori. שמעון
שגינה, Shimon shegina, שמעון Shimon that spoke negatively, יהרג, yehareg, he shall
be put to death. Now by the way, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai was very oppressed by the Romans, you know,
so whatever the historical truth of this story is, you know, the
fact is whether and whether that was what led him to say
those negative things or, you know, or not, but this certainly it
is reflecting a historical reality. Okay, so אזל הוא וברה. azal hu
u'vreh. By the way there's also a very famous גמרא Gemara that
makes almost does the parallel of this, you know, with who is
it? With פרעה's Paroh's three advisors, right? What was it? יתרו, Yisro,
בלעם, Bilaam, יתרו, Yisro, בלעם, Bilaam, and איוב, Iyov, right, right. So
you know, so בלעם Bilaam agreed, so he, he, he gets killed,
right? יתרו Yisro opposed and then איוב Iyov was silent and that's
why he suffered the punishment. Yes, so it's an interesting sort of
like, you know, similar type of a, of literary theme. So anyway,
device. So anyway, let's take a look. So what did he do?
אזל הוא וברה, azal hu u'vreh, so he and his son went,
interesting, his son didn't do anything but I guess he didn't want
to be alone, so he and his son went, טשו בבי מדרשא,
tashu b'vei medrasha, they held, they hid in the בית מדרש. beis
medrash. It sounds like his son was, felt he was under some
threat. כל יומא הוה מייתי ליה דביתהו ריפתא וכוזא דמיא, Kol yoma
hava mayti leh d'veiteihu rifta v'kuza d'maya, every day his wife would
bring him bread and a flask of water, וכרכי, v'karchi, and they
would, literally means wrap, they would eat the bread. כי תקיף גזירתא,
Ki takif gezeirasa, when the, when the edict grew stronger like they
were, you know, really more vigorously looking for him, אמר ליה לברה,
amar leh l'vreh, he said to his son, נשים דעתן קלה עליהן,
nashim da'atan kala aleihen, women have a, they're sort of, you know,
not as, I don't even know how to translate, anyway, the knowledge
is, anyway, we'll see, we'll see what he means. He does not
mean they're stupid. Let's take a look what he means. He says,
דילמא מצערי לה ומגליה לן. dilma m'tzari lah u'mgalya lan. He's not
afraid that סתם stam she'll just reveal, but you know, maybe they'll,
right, they'll torture her and she'll reveal us. torture her and she
won't be able to withstand it. So that's an interesting use of
דעתן קלה, Daatan Kala, which means they won't be able to, like,
resist, you know, certain types of pressure. Anyway, so what should we
do? אזל טשו במערתא. Azal tishu b'mearta. So they went and they
hid in a cave. איתרחיש ניסא, Itrachish nisa, so a miracle happened.
איברי להו חרובא, Ivrei lehu charuva, so a carob tree, you know,
popped up, or was created, ועינא דמיא, v'eina d'maya, and a wellspring
of water. והוו משלחי מניהו, V'havu mashlechi maneihu, they would take off
their clothes, והוו יתבי עד צואריהו בחלא, v'havu yatvi ad tzavreihu b'chala,
and they would sit to their necks in sand.
So why Rashi says? Well, the plan is they're going to be
there a long time, they only have one set of clothes, they
don't want to wear out their clothes. So they had... so why
were they sitting in sand? So it's because they want to learn,
you don't want to be naked. Except I don't know why it
has to be up to your neck, could be up to your
waist, I don't know. Anyway, I'm sure there's a lot you could
do with this midrashically, there's a lot you could...
okay.
בחלא. B'chala. כל יומא גרסי, Kol yoma garsi, every day they would
learn, בעידן צלויי, b'idan tzaluye, when it came time to דאוון daven
because I guess then you should be standing on the ground and
not buried in sand, לבושו, lavshu, they put on their clothes. So
they put on their clothes once a day to דאוון, daven, מכסו,
michsu, they would cover themselves, ומצלו, u'metzalu, and they would
דאוון. daven. והדר משלחי מניהו, V'hadar mashlechi maneihu, and then they'd take
their clothes off, כי היכי דלא ליבלו, ki heichi d'lo livlu, so
it shouldn't... they should not wear out. יתבו תריסר שני במערתא, Yatvu
treisar shani b'mearta, they stayed there for twelve years in the cave.
אתא אליהו, Ata Eliyahu, so Elijah came, וקם אפיתחא דמערתא, v'kam afitcha
d'mearta, he stood by the opening of the cave. אמר, Amar, מאן
לודעיה לבר יוחי דמית קיסר ובטלה גזירתיה? man lodeyei l'Bar Yochai d'mit
Keisar u'batla gzeirateih? Who can... who will tell Bar Yochai that the
Caesar has died and the edict is annulled? So again, why didn't
he just go and tell them directly? I don't know. Anyway, it's
also, by the way, mentioning אליהו Eliyahu here, and אליהו, Eliyahu, you
know, being in the cave, and, right, and, there's an interest... I
think there's an interesting parallel, right? The ravens were bringing him food,
right? And here you have... so you have this miraculous way of
being... of surviving in the cave. But I don't know in the
context of the story why אליהו Eliyahu is not actually telling them
directly, just sort of saying in passing. Anyway, maybe you believe it
more that way, מסיח לפי תומו, misiach lefi tumo, because often אליהו
Eliyahu appears in disguise. נפקו חזו אינשי דקא כרבי וזרעי. Nafku chazu
inshi d'ka karbi v'zari. So they came out of the cave and
they saw people that were plowing and planting. אמר, Amar, מניחין חיי
עולם ועוסקין בחיי שעה. menichin chayei olam v'oskin b'chayei sha'ah. So here,
they've been in the cave for twelve years, all they know is...
is learning, they can't... they can no longer relate to the real
world. So they said, look at these people, they're leaving the eternal
life and they're dealing with temporal needs, they're bothering about planting.
כל מקום שנותנין עיניהם. Kol makom shenotnin eineihem. By the way, I
mean, it's obvious the connection in the גמרא Gemara in ברכות, Berachot,
you learn right before this about... about whether it's... what is
it? About whether... the גמרא Gemara about, you know,
the
מחלוקת machloket of Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai and others, whether it's... oh,
what's the פסוק? pasuk?
Why am I not remembering? Anyway, but it's about whether with the
פסוקים pesukim that speak about your plant and your harvest, right, they're
from the שמע, Shema, I don't know what's going on with my
brain. Is it about, you know, תורתו אומנתו? torato umnato? So, you
know, the גמרא Gemara there says, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says, you
know, if you're זכו, zachu, other people will go ahead and take
care of your planting and your harvesting and you'll be able to
sit and learn תורה Torah the whole day. It's a מחלוקת machloket
about, you know, whether you're supposed to devote yourself completely to תורה
Torah and assume that other people are going to take care of
it, or whether you're supposed to actually devote yourself to a פרנסה.
parnassah. So here, obviously it connects to this story.
So, כל מקום שנותנין עיניהם מיד נשרף. kol makom shenotnin eineihem miyad
nisraf.
Anywhere they would put their eye, they would look... give their evil
eye to people who they did not like were bothering with temporal
needs, they would be, you know, the people would be burnt... burnt
up. יצתה בת קול ואמרה להם, Yatzta bat kol v'amra lahem, להחריב
עולמי יצאתם? l'hachriv olami yetzatem? A heavenly
voice came out and said to them, 'To destroy my world you
came out?' חזרו למערתכם, Chizru l'mearatchem, go back to your cave. הדר
אזלו יתבו תריסר ירחי שתא. Hadar azlu yatvu treisar yarchei shata. They
went there and instead of twelve years, they waited twelve months. אמרי,
Amri, משפט רשעים בגיהנום י"ב חודש. mishpat reshaim b'gehinnom yud-bet chodesh. Look,
even רשעים reshaim are only in גיהנום gehinnom for twelve months. So
whatever we did wrong, maybe this will be a כפרה. kapara. יצתה
בת קול ואמרה, Yatzta bat kol v'amra, צאו ממערתכם. tze'u m'mearatchem.
So then, when they sort of themselves were presumably feeling it was
time to go out, a heavenly voice came out and said, 'Leave
your cave.' כל היכא דהוה מחי רבי אלעזר הוה מסי רבי שמעון.
Kol heicha d'hava machi Rabbi Elazar hava masi Rabbi Shimon. Wherever Rabbi
Elazar would smite, Rabbi Elazar still didn't learn his lesson, the son,
Rabbi Shimon would heal. So again, I'm not exactly sure how this
whole Rabbi Elazar plays in, like why he was under the edict,
why he didn't learn the lesson as well as Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai, where Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai was able to sort of get
the lesson, and Rabbi Elazar, and he's younger, so maybe he's more
idealistic. But anyway, there's, you know, within the context of the story,
that's not explained. אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to him, בני
די לעולם אני ואתה. beni dai l'olam ani v'ata. Look, don't worry,
you and I, we're enough to keep the תורה Torah going for
the world, you don't have to worry about other people. Okay, so
sort of maybe played into his own sort of sense of ego,
you know, but also, give other people a break.
You can have high standards for yourself. ובהדי פניא דמעלי שבתא, V'bahadei
panya d'ma'alei shabta, חזו ההוא סבא דהוה נקיט תרי מדאני אסא. chazu
hahu saba d'hava nakit terei madanei asa. It was right when it
was ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, they saw a certain old person holding
on to two bunches of
myrtle. And he was running בין השמשות bein hashmashos right before שבת
shabbos to running home. אמרו ליה הני למה לך amru lei hanei
lama lach why why you have these? אמר להו לכבוד שבת. amar
lehu lichvod shabbos. I'm doing it to honor שבת. shabbos. So he
said חד כנגד זכור וחד כנגד שמור. chad kineged zachor v'chad kineged
shamor. So one should be enough? No. חד כנגד זכור וחד כנגד
שמור chad kineged zachor v'chad kineged shamor one for זכור zachor and
one for שמור. shamor. אמר ליה לברה amar lei l'breih so he
said to his son חזי כמה חביבין מצות עלי ישראל. chazi kama
chavivin mitzvos alei Yisrael. Oh, look how dear the מצות mitzvos of
ישראל. Yisrael. Don't give them such a hard time. Others don't know
תורה Torah as much as you but the מצות mitzvos that are
accessible to them, look at how much they value it and how
much they go out of their way and they don't just יוצא
yotzei but it's really
חביבין. chavivin. יתיב דעתייהו yasiv daiteihu so they felt better. Again it's
interesting יתיב דעתייהו yasiv daiteihu in the plural. He's now the one
educating his son but somehow it's יתיב דעתייהו, yasiv daiteihu, at least
this גרסא, girsa, I don't know if there are other גרסות girsos
about this. Okay. שמע רבי
פנחס בן יאיר חתניה, shama Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair chasnei, רבי פנחס
בן יאיר Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair his son-in-law heard that רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai was heading back, finally came out
of the cave, ונפק לאפיה v'nafik l'appei and he went to greet
him. עייליה לבי בני aylei l'bei banei he brought him into the
bathhouse. קאריך k'arich
it's interesting, wonders if the earlier discussion was about the bathhouses. I'm
still trying to figure out how this whole story about the cave,
if in any way does it connect back to the whole issue
about attitudes towards the Romans or whatever, maybe he was more detached
from the world. If you're more in the world you more appreciate
the benefits that you receive from the larger world, if you're all
in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash you can sort of dismiss it
all.
He did learn his lesson, right. So let's see, the story isn't
over yet. Okay, so he brought him into the bathhouse. קאריך ליה
לבשריה k'arich lei l'bisrei he was massaging his flesh. חזא דהוה ביה
פילי בגופיה chazei d'hava bei pili b'gufei he saw that there were
cracks in the flesh from sitting in the sand for 12 years.
הוה קבכי hava k'bachi he was crying, this is רבי פנחס בן
יאיר. Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair.
וקנשרו דמעת עינוהי v'k'nasru dimas einohi so the tears from his eyes
were falling וקמצוחא ליה v'k'mitztavcha lei and they were causing him, as
רש"י Rashi says it was actually causing pain to רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai because the tears, the salty tears were
falling onto the skin. Anyway אמר ליה אוי לי שראיתיך בכך amar
lei oi li she're'isicha b'kach so פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas ben Yair
said woe that I've seen you this way, how destroyed your body
has become. אמר ליה אשריך שראיתני בכך amar lei ashrecha she're'isani b'kach
praised are you that you've seen me this way, שאילמלי לא ראיתני
בכך she'ilmalei lo re'isani b'kach had you not seen me this way
לא מצאת בי כך lo matzasa bi kach
you would not have found with me the level of תורה Torah
that I have now achieved. So by sort of mortifying my body.
דמעיקרא d'me'ikara because originally כי הוה מקשי רבי שמעון בר יוחאי קושיא
ki hava makshi Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai kushia when רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai used to ask a question הוה מפרק
ליה רבי פנחס בן יאיר תריסר פירוקי hava parik lei Rabbi Pinchas
ben Yair treisar perukei רבי פנחס בן יאיר Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair
would have 12 answers to it. ולסוף u'lesof at the end after
this period in the cave כי הוה מקשי רבי פנחס בן יאיר
קושיא ki hava makshi Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair kushia when פנחס בן
יאיר Pinchas ben Yair would ask a question הוה מפרק ליה רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי עשרין וארבעה פירוקי hava parik lei Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai esrin v'arba perukei so רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai had 24 answers, so he surpassed his
master his son-in-law and to a far greater extent. אמר הואיל ואיתרחיש
ניסא amar ho'il v'itchish nisa now that this miracle has occurred to
me, I was saved, איזיל אתקין מילתא eizil askin milsa let me
go and try to fix something. What does this mean? דכתיב ויבא
יעקב שלם d'ksiv vayavo Yaakov shalem יעקב Yaakov came full to the
city of שכם. Shechem. אמר רב שלם בגופו שלם בממונו amar Rav
shalem b'gufo shalem b'mamono
he was full not only in his body after the fight with
the angel but in his wealth, שלם בתורתו shalem b'Toraso his תורה,
Torah, none of that had been injured by his stay with
עשו. Esav. Excuse me, not עשו Esav but with לבן. Lavan. ויחן
את פני העיר vayichan es p'nei ha'ir
he encamped by the face of the city. אמר
רב amar Rav מה משמע ויחן, ma mashma vayichan, he did something
for the city, he gave חן chen as רש"י Rashi says to
the city. So he established coinage for them, actually that ties into
what we're going to be learning today. ושמואל אמר שווקי תיקן להם
v'Shmuel amar shvaki tikein lahem he made city squares, markets. ורבי יוחנן
אמר מרחצאות תיקן להם v'Rabbi Yochanan amar merchatzaos tikein lahem does any
of this sound familiar? Who did the שווקי shvaki and the מרחצאות
merchatzaos and the מטבעות? matbei'os? That was all the Romans, right? So
now יעקב Yaakov is the one that now did this for שכם
Shechem for the non-Jew. So it's okay if the Jews are providing
it for the non-Jews but not the other way around. Oh yeah.
An excellent point.
Isn't רשב"י Rashbi doing this for the Romans now?
Wait, let's see who he's going to do it for. This was
first of all יעקב Yaakov did for שכם, Shechem, okay? So אמר
amar so רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai said איכא
מילתא דבעי לאתקוני ika milsa d'ba'ei l'iskun is there something here I
can help to give to the city to help because this miracle
was done for me? I came out full in my תורה, Torah,
full in my body after it got recovered. So אמרו ליה amru
lei they said איכא דוכתא דאית בה ספק טומאה ika duchta d'is
bei safek tumah there's a place that has doubtful טומאה tumah and
we'll just read one line, you don't know if there's טומאה tumah
just beginning of ל"ד עמוד א' Lamed Daled amud aleph and in
the middle of like some marketplace or some public square. ואית ליה
צערא לכהנים לאקופי v'is lei tza'ara l'kohanim l'akufi very difficult, the כהנים
kohanim have to go around it rather than going through it. It
makes them go out of their way for miles or whatever. So
we'd like to it would be great if we could know where
is the dead bodies here. אמר איכא איניש דידע דאיתחזק הכא טהרה
amar ika inish d'yadi d'is-chazaki hacha tahara does somebody know that there
was used to be טהרה tahara here? all a graveyard. אמר ליה
ההוא סבא *amar lei hahu saba*, so a certain elder said to
him, כאן קיצץ בן זכאי תורמוסי תרומה *kan kitzetz ben zakai turmusei
terumah*. Here בן זכאי *Ben Zakai* cut these like these cuttings of
תרומה *terumah*, which means רש״י *Rashi* says it means he planted תרומה
*terumah* here, which must mean that it's acceptable, to you know, that
it's טהור *tahor*, or he wouldn't have planted תרומה *terumah* here. There's
questions about planting תרומה *terumah* and גידולי תרומה *gidulei terumah*, but anyway,
some here בן זכאי *Ben Zakai* handled תרומה *terumah* in this space
so they definitely was, it was this space was okay a while
ago. It wasn't always. Of course now there are problems, there are
places there are problems, but you know, definitely we knew it was
okay at one time. So עבד איהו נמי הכי *avad ihu nami
hachi*, so he did similarly, similarly to who? To בן זכאי *Ben
Zakai*. תוספות *Tosafot* says it means similarly to יעקב אבינו Yaakov Avinu,
*Yaakov Avinu*. But anyway, maybe he thought that when בן זכאי *Ben
Zakai* did it, it was to demonstrate that it was טהור *tahor*.
Anyway, so what did he do? כל היכא דהוה קשי טהריה *kol
hacha d'hava kashi taharei*, any place where the ground was hard, virgin
earth, he said it's טהור *tahor*, nothing is buried here. וכל היכא
דהוה רפי צייניה *v'chol hacha d'hava rafi tzyneih*, whenever it was, whenever
it was like
soft, he marked it, that this is where there might be a
grave. So now at least there are spots that are okay that
the כהנים *kohanim* could cut through. אמר ההוא סבא *amar hahu saba*,
so this elder person who was part of this discussion said, טיהר
בן יוחאי בית הקברות *teher ben yochai beit hakevarot*, it's like you
purified a, you know, a cemetery. This whole thing we assumed had
קברים *kevarim* and you said oh this is okay, this is okay.
אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said to him, אלמלי היית עמנו
ואפילו היית עמנו ולא נמנית עמנו יפה אתה אומר *ilmalei hayita imanu
v'afilu hayita imanu v'lo nimneita imanu yafeh atah omer*. Look, if you
weren't in the conversation that we just had about trying to figure
out what's what, or if you were in the conversation but weren't
in the vote, I could understand you'd have a right to critique.
עכשיו שהיית עמנו *achshav shehayita imanu*, you were part of the whole
process, ונמנית עמנו *v'nimneita imanu*, and you were in the decision and
the vote, and still you're critiquing and you're calling me names and
you're saying I was מטהר בית הקברות *metaher beit hakevarot*, which was
not a compliment, so יאמרו זונות מפרכסות זו את זו תלמידי חכמים
לא כל שכן *yomru zonot mefarkesot zo et zo talmidei chachamim lo
kol shekein*. If prostitutes will adorn one another, so how much more
so תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*, so even if we're in competition it's
still could be a type of competition where you help out one
another and you compliment and you don't attack them and so on.
So how dare you attack me. So יהב ביה עינא ונח נפשיה
*yahav beih eina v'nach nafsheih*, he gave him the eye and he
died. So so much for attacking people, the eye for plowing and
planting, but for disagreeing with him and challenging his authority. Now wait,
it's not over. נפק לשוקא *nafak l'shuka*, he went out to the
שוק *shuk*, notice again the שוק *shuk*, חזייה ליהודה בן גרים *chazyei
l'yehudah ben geirim*, and he saw יהודה בן גרים *Yehudah Ben Geirim*,
the guy whose loose lips sink ships. Right. By the way, it
just occurred to me right now, one of the big themes before
about עשיו *Esau* was לשון הרע *lashon hara*. So even if he
was not like willfully tattling, it was still like, you know, not
being careful with his speech. אמר עדיין יש לזה בעולם *amar adayin
yesh lazeh ba'olam*, this guy's still alive. So נתן בו עיניו ונעשה
גל של עצמות *natan bo einav v'na'aseh gal shel atzamot*. Exactly.
We will end the דף *daf* today. So I do want to
say a
beautiful story of forgiveness.
So I just do want to say about this issue though about
notice his תיקון *tikun* was only for within the Jewish community.
Right.
I think he I think the גמרא *Gemara* thinks that he did
the things יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* did, לדורון *l'doron*.
I think that's what רש״י *Rashi* says here.
No, that's what רש״י *Rashi*...
כדרך שעשה יעקב Yaakov *kederech she'asah
yaakov*. I know, but כדרך *kederech*. Right.
So his תקנה *takanah* was, I'll say I'll provide fifteen reasons the
way I'm reading it. Okay. I don't think that's, wait, wait, no.
תוספות *Tosafot* on... תוספות *Tosafot*, not רש״י *Rashi*. תוספות *Tosafot*, מפרש התם
דמו ליעקב דתיקן להם *mefaresh hatam damu l'yaakov d'tikan lahem*.
כמי *K'mi*, like he's doing the...
Yes, but what did he do? עבד איהו נמי הכי *avad ihu
nami hachi* and he fixed up this place.
איכא דאמרי מילתא *ika d'amrei milta*. Okay. So it's a מחלוקת רש״י
ותוספות *machloket Rashi v'Tosafot*. Which רש״י *Rashi* is that? I think תיקן
מילתא *itken milta* the bottom of ל״ג ע״ב *lamed gimmel amud bet*.
כדרך שעשה יעקב Yaakov *kederech she'asah yaakov*.
תיקן להם *tikan lahem*, but up above that.
תיקן מילתא *itken milta* before four lines up from there. One, two...
Okay. כדרך שעשה יעקב כשנכנס *kederech she'asah yaakov k'shenichnas*. Yeah.
כדרך
*kederech* what? But the תיקן מילתא *itken milta* spells out what the
תיקן מילתא *itken milta*.
No, but רש״י *Rashi*'s doing the things that יעקב *Yaakov* did.
I think that is, okay, I don't agree. I think it means
the same way יעקב *Yaakov* did something, I'm going to do something.
But his thing was helping, was helping out, I think that the
lesson is that there's still יעקב *Yaakov*, he hasn't yet, he still
hasn't been fully
redeemed in this whole being מטהר *metaher* the בית הקברות *beit hakevarot*.
Is it a trope taken from someplace else? Does it exist in
the version that exists in other places?
Oh, that's a different question whether whether the original text has been,
this has been grafted on. That's a different issue.
But then he claims that the תקנה *takanah* of רשב״י *Rashbi* was
to do the things that יעקב *Yaakov* did.
I understand. If you don't have the "and" here, you might be
right. So that's a different argument of whether the original text didn't
have the "and". But in terms of the way it's presented. Right,
that might be. But in the way it's presented here, I think
that's a very forced read. But if the argument is that other
texts don't have the "and". It's also
clear that
whoever
redacted the story clearly put it together because he put the end
on to tie the whole thing together.
I think the way we have it, רשב״י *Rashbi* has still not
moved so much. He's still... Killing people he doesn't like. He's still
only doing it for the Jewish community. Right? You're right. If you
ended before that, it would have been beautiful, because he taught his
son the lesson, he taught more forgiveness, he gave back to the
community exactly the same types of things that he was saying like
that the Romans did for them. So if you, you're right, if
you ended at the bottom of ל"ג, it's a much different ending.
Then do you think רב, Rav, שמואל, Shmuel, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan are saying those things about יעקב in שכם? Shechem?
Yes, totally. And that is totally how it is, how it is
in other texts. That's completely a דרשה drasha on ויחן את פני
העיר. Vayichan et pnei ha'ir. No, that, you, that definitely. But I'm
just saying, if you did not have the end after that, you
ended with יעקב אבינו, then it's beautiful, then he becomes more forgiving,
he's the same things יעקב did and he appreciated, he gives back.
So the whole thing changes by this thing at the end. So
I'd like to see the proofs that, how that stuff ended up
there. Okay. Sort of like if
you
ended the יעקב story...